Guide to the Collection of Oxford and Cambridge Bookplates
Yale University Arts Library
Collection of Oxford and Cambridge Bookplates
1632-1955
1700-1894
BKP 54
Yale University Arts Library
0.83
(2 boxes)
This collection includes bookplates of the various residential colleges affiliated with the University of Oxford and the University of Cambridge, both of which are located in England.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Yale Bookplate Collection was formerly housed in Sterling Memorial Library. The collection was incorporated into the Arts of the Book Collection in 1984 and then moved to the Seeley G. Mudd Library in 1990. In 2011, it was transferred to the Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes bookplates for the various residential colleges affiliated with the University of Oxford or the University of Cambridge, both of which are located in England.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Bookplates – Oxford. II. Bookplates – Cambridge.
Bookplates; Bookplates; University of Oxford; University of Cambridge
- Bookplates – Oxford, Series I
  Arrangement
  Bookplates are arranged according to the similarity of their mounts.
  - Oxford Colleges, circa 1760 undated; 45 items (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    This folder contains 45 bookplates which were all housed in a portfolio labeled "Bookplates of Colleges of Oxford." The portfolio, individual mounts, and bookplates often bear the collector's stamp of A. Bernard C. K. Keeves as well as annotations in his hand. The portfolio also contains a couple of examples of supralibros, which are ex-libris designs stamped on the exterior of a book cover.
  - Oxford Colleges, undated; 20 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Oxford Colleges, 1703 undated; 23 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Oxford Colleges, undated; 21 items (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Oxford Colleges, 1702-1704 undated; 22 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Oxford Colleges, undated; 20 items (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Oxford Colleges, 1894 undated; 20 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Oxford Colleges, undated; 18 items (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Oxford Colleges, undated; 26 items (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Oxford Colleges, 1894 undated; 20 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Oxford Colleges, 1703-1903 undated; 15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Oxford Colleges, undated; 16 items (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Oxford Colleges, 1903-1904 undated; 17 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ephemera, undated; 24 items (Box 1, Folder 14)
    This folder contains ephemeral material related to the Oxford series, including mounts without attached bookplates and hand-written lists of Oxford Colleges.
- Bookplates – Cambridge, Series II
  - Cambridge Colleges, 1700-1842 undated; 60 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    This folder contains 60 bookplates which are all housed in a portfolio labeled "Bookplates of Colleges of Cambridge." The portfolio, individual mounts, and bookplates often bear the collector's stamp of A. Bernard C. K. Keeves as well as annotations in his hand. The portfolio also contains an undated piece of correspondence from Trinity Lodge, Cambridge.
  - Cambridge Colleges, undated; 20 items (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Cambridge Colleges, undated; 20 items (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Cambridge Colleges, undated; 20 items (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Cambridge Colleges, 1719-1859 undated; 21 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Cambridge Colleges, 1700-1879 undated; 17 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    This folder contains an exhibition label regarding the first and second states of the armorial bookplate of Queens College, Cambridge, dated 1700. The label recounts an anecdote from Dr. J. S. Pearson regarding the discovery of the first state, which includes a mistake in the quartering of the coat of arms. This folder also contains an envelope with photographic reproductions of the two states of this bookplate.
  - Cambridge Colleges, 1707-1874 undated; 19 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Cambridge Colleges, 1637-1935 undated; 21 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Cambridge Colleges, 1632-1736 undated; 20 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Cambridge Colleges, 1879 undated; 21 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Cambridge Colleges, 1700-1842 undated; 21 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Cambridge Colleges, undated; 24 items (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Cambridge Colleges, 1929-1955 undated; 25 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    This folder contains 25 bookplates or other printed materials for King's College, Cambridge. They are housed in an envelope which states that they are the gift of A. N. L. Munby, 1962. The personal ex-libris of Munby is also included among the bookplates.
  - Cambridge Colleges, 1715 undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Ephemera, undated; 13 items (Box 2, Folder 29)
    This folder contains ephemeral material related to the Cambridge series, including mounts without attached bookplates.